John Alden Mason Papers 1904-1967 Mss.B.M384
American Philosophical Society
- Series I. Correspondence, 1926-1967; 20 linear feet
  - Tschopik, Harry, Jr., 1942-1956 (Box 37)
  - Tsuru, Shigeto (Box 37)
  - Tucker, Sara Jones (Box 37)
  - Tulane University (Box 37)
    - Dept. of Middle American Research (Box 37)
      - Ries, Maurice (Box 37)
      - Gropp, Arthur (Box 37)
  - Turner, Glen (Box 37)
  - Turney-High, Harry (Box 37)
    - Flint, Elaine N (Box 37)
  - University of Pennsylvania. Committee on Latin American Studies (Box 37)
  - Uhle, Max (Box 37)
  - Uhlenbeck, C. C (Box 37)
  - Uitgeveric Contact (Box 37)
  - Ullrich, Hans (Box 37)
  - Umpleby, P. C (Box 37)
  - Underhill, Ruth M. (Box 37)
    - Mathiot, Madeleine (Box 37)
  - Underhill, Ruth M, 1931-1953 (Box 37)
  - United Fruit Company (Box 37)
  - U.S. Anthropometric work; (Has C.B.Davenport materisls), July-Sept., 1919 (Box 37)
  - U.S. Department of the Interior (Box 37)
  - U. S. Dept. of State [also] Mexico (Box 37)
  - U.S. Government Printing Office (Box 37)
    - Eastin, Roy B (Box 37)
    - Wiggins, Mrs. John C (Box 37)
  - U. S. Office of Education (Box 37)
    - Beust, Nora E (Box 37)
  - U.S. Office of Indian Affairs (Box 37)
  - University Museum: Loans Granted (Box 37)
  - University Museum: Loans Received (Box 38)
  - University of California Press (Box 38)
    - Becker (Box 38)
    - Dolores, Juan (Box 38)
    - Dolores, Sylvia Beyer (Box 38)
    - Niehaus, Hazel (Box 38)
  - University of Pennsylvania Club of N.Y.C (Box 38)
    - Martin, Luther, III (Box 38)
  - Universidad de Costa Rica (Box 38)
  - University Museum. History (Box 38)
  - Unknown (Box 38)
  - Urban, Adala (Box 38)
  - Urban, Adda Maria (Box 38)
  - Urbanski, Edmund Stephen (Box 38)
  - Urruela E., Herlinda (Box 38)
  - Vaillant, George C., Memoir by Alfonso Caso (Box 38)
  - Vaillant, George C., Memoir (Box 38)
  - Vaillant, George C (Box 38)
    - Johnson, Frederick (Box 38)
    - Tozzer, Alfred M (Box 38)
    - Vaillant, Sue (Box 38)
  - Valcarcel, Luis E (Box 38)
    - Satterthwaite, Linton, Jr (Box 38)
  - Valdes, Carlos Angula (Box 38)
  - Valentini, Evelyn Ernest (Box 38)
  - Valin, W B van (Box 38)
  - Valle, M. M (Box 38)
  - Valle, Rafael Heliodoro (Box 38)
  - Valles, Rafael (Box 38)
  - Valley Forge Military Academy (Box 38)
  - Valley Forge Park Commission (Box 38)
    - Wright, Norris D (Box 38)
  - Van Deventer, Early (Box 38)
  - Van Giffen Duyvis, Mrs. Guda E G (Box 38)
  - Van Stan, Ina (Box 38)
  - Van Valin, W. B (Box 38)
  - Vargas, Ezequiel B (Box 38)
  - Vargas, Jorge Riquelme (Box 38)
  - Vargus, Jesus (Box 38)
    - Solenberger, Robert R (Box 38)
  - Vaughn, George (Box 38)
  - Veach, Challes (Box 38)
  - Venuto, Paul B (Box 38)
  - Verdoorn, Frans (Box 38)
  - Verges, Eugene M II (Box 38)
  - Vernon, Louis H (Box 38)
  - Verrill, A Hyatt (Box 38)
  - Vestby, Anton (Box 38)
  - Victor, Paul E (Box 38)
  - Viking Fund (Box 38)
    - Binns, Lita (Box 38)
    - Fekos, Paul (Box 38)
    - Fisher, Jane E (Box 38)
    - Sweet, Joan (Box 38)
    - Wenner-Gren, Axel L (Box 38)
  - Villacorta C,J Antonio (Box 38)
    - Satterthwaite, Linton, Jr (Box 38)
  - Villacorta C., J Antonio (Box 38)
  - Villacorta, Carlos A (Box 38)
  - Villegas, Eduardo Risso (Box 38)
  - Vivó, Jorge A (Box 38)
  - Voegelin, Carl F (Box 38)
    - Hoebel, E Adamson (Box 38)
    - Steward, Julian H (Box 38)
    - Voegelin, Erminie W (Box 38)
  - Vogt, Evon Z (Box 38)
  - Von Hagen, Victor (Box 38)
    (see also: Hagen, victor...)
  - Voorhees, Russell Raymond (Box 38)
  - Waddington, Mrs. C. F (Box 39)
  - Wade, Joe S (Box 39)
  - Wafford, J. A (Box 39)
  - Wagenman, R. C (Box 39)
  - Wagley, Charles, 1942; 2 items (Box 39)
    Re: Tupi and other languages of Brazil.
  - Wagner, Arthur (Box 39)
  - Wagner, D. H (Box 39)
    - Jayne, Horace H F (Box 39)
    - Lippincott, Mrs William J (Box 39)
    - Satterthwaite, Linton, Jr (Box 39)
  - Wagner, Daniel Hobson (Box 39)
  - Wagner, Joseph A (Box 39)
  - Wagner, Sallie (Box 39)
  - Waldegg, Hermann von (Box 39)
  - Walde-Waldegg, Hermann von (Box 39)
  - Walker, Ernest P (Box 39)
  - Walker, Lester C.,Jr (Box 39)
  - Wallace, Anthony J (Box 39)
  - Wallace, John (Box 39)
  - Wallace, Paul A. W (Box 39)
  - Wallach, Phillip (Box 39)
  - Wallis, David Edward (Box 39)
  - Wallis, Wilson D (Box 39)
  - Wallis, Wilson D (Box 39)
    - Colson, Elizabeth (Box 39)
    - Mason, Leonard (Box 39)
  - Walter, A. J (Box 39)
  - Walter, Mary I (Box 39)
  - Walters, Madge Hardin (Box 39)
  - Walther, Jayne (Box 39)
  - Walton, Miss (Box 39)
  - War Eagle (Chief) (Box 39)
  - Ward, Bruce H (Box 39)
  - Ward, Henry L (Box 39)
  - Warden, Betty (Box 39)
  - Wardle, Harriet Newell (Box 39)
  - Warner, Benjamin F., Jr (Box 39)
  - Warner, Mason (Box 39)
  - Warner, Paul (Box 39)
  - Warren, Phelps (Box 39)
  - Warren, Richard Fairfield (Box 39)
  - Washburn, Georgia C (Box 39)
  - Washburn, Joan (Box 39)
  - Washington, Mrs. Thomas (Box 39)
  - Wassén, Henry (Box 39)
    - Fejos, Paul (Box 39)
    - Holmer, Nils M (Box 39)
  - Wass, Robert H., Jr (Box 39)
  - Waterman, Richard Alan (Box 39)
    - Alegria, Ricardo E (Box 39)
  - Waterman, T. T (Box 39)
  - Waters, Mrs. J Newland (Box 39)
  - Watsey, G[azel] Wallington (Box 39)
    - Gleason, Edward J (Box 39)
    - Satterthwaite, Linton, Jr (Box 39)
  - Watson, Don (Box 39)
  - Watson, James B (Box 39)
  - Wauchope, Robert (Box 39)
  - Way, Ivan M (Box 39)
    - Johnson, Frederick (Box 39)
  - Waynesburg College (Box 39)
    - Stewart, Paul R (Box 39)
  - Weaver, Frank M (Box 39)
  - Webb, Maurice Pownall (Box 39)
  - Webb, William S (Box 39)
    - Snow, Charles E (Box 39)
  - Webb, William S (Box 39)
  - Webster, Gloria (Box 39)
    - Satterthwaite, Linton, Jr (Box 39)
  - Webster, Mrs. Eleanor (Box 39)
  - Weckler, Joseph E (Box 39)
  - Wedel, Waldo R (Box 39)
  - Weer, Paul W (Box 39)
  - Weiford, Mrs. Richard P (Box 39)
  - Weigand, Phil C., 1966-1967; 4 items (Box 39)
  - Weinberg, Gladys D (Box 39)
  - Weinberger, Bernhard Wolf (Box 39)
  - Weinrott, George H & Co (Box 39)
  - Weir, Walter, Inc (Box 39)
  - Weisbard, Ruth (Box 39)
  - Weiss, Arnold H (Box 39)
  - Weiss, Irving J (Box 39)
  - Weiss, Myron (Box 39)
  - Weitlaner, Robert J (Box 39)
  - Weitzner, Bella (Box 39)
  - Weller, E. B (Box 39)
  - Wellford, Roberta (Box 39)
  - Welsh, George A (Box 39)
  - Welsh, John H (Box 39)
    - Bird, Junius B (Box 39)
  - Weltfish, Gene (Box 39)
  - Wenger, Clarence W (Box 39)
  - Wenger, Joseph (Box 39)
  - Wenner-Gren, Axel L (Box 39)
  - Weslager, C. A (Box 39)
  - Wessén, Henry (Box 39)
  - Wessel, Walter E (Box 39)
  - Wessels, Helen E (Box 39)
  - West, George A (Box 39)
  - West, Mrs. Dorothy A. (William H) (Box 39)
  - West, Robert C (Box 39)
  - Westmoreland, Harriett (Box 39)
    - Freiberg, Bernice (Box 39)
  - Wetherill, William C (Box 39)
    - Rice, James J (Box 39)
  - Wetmore, A (Box 39)
  - Weygold, Frederick (Box 39)
  - Wharton, James B (Box 39)
  - Wheeler, Jane (Box 39)
  - Wheeler, Joseph L (Box 39)
  - Wheeler, Walter S (Box 39)
  - When Doctors Disagree (Box 39)
  - Whent, E R (Box 39)
  - Whipple, Mary Anne (Box 39)
  - Whistler, Don (Box 39)
  - Whitaker, Arthur P (Box 39)
  - White, Alma E (Box 39)
  - White, Anne (Box 39)
  - White, James T & Co (Box 39)
    - Mason, William A (Box 39)
  - White, Leslie A (Box 39)
  - White, Walter N (Box 39)
  - Whitecraft, Earl B (Box 39)
  - Whiteford, Andrew Hunter (Box 39)
  - Whitehouse, Sheldon (Box 39)
  - Whitlock, C. E. S (Box 39)
  - Whitney, Alvin G (Box 39)
  - Whitney, Philippa (Box 39)
  - Whitney, Vincent H (Box 39)
  - Whittemore, Jeanette Springstead (Box 39)
  - Whorf, Benjamin L, 1928-1935 (Box 39)
  - Who's Who in America (Box 39)
  - Who's Who in American Education (Box 39)
    - Cook, Robert C (Box 39)
    - Smith, Mary Alice (Box 39)
  - Who's Who in the East (Box 39)
  - Who's Who in the Western Hemisphere (Box 39)
    - Rocker, R (Box 39)
  - Wickendem, W E (Box 39)
  - Wiedenmayer Joseph E (Box 39)
  - Wieschoff, Heinz A (Box 39)
  - Wilbur, Anna Dean (Box 39)
  - Wilbur, Walter Karl (Box 39)
    - Barlow, R H (Box 39)
    - Braunholtz, H J (Box 39)
    - Department of State, Passport Division (Box 39)
    - Thomas, Wilbur K (Box 39)
  - Wilcoxson, Emily M (Box 40)
  - Wildes, Harry Emerson (Box 40)
  - Wilgus, A Curtis (Box 40)
  - Wilkes, R. R (Box 40)
  - Wilkins, E. P (Box 40)
  - Wilkins, Elwood (Box 40)
  - Wilkins, Harold T (Box 40)
  - Wilkins, Percy (Box 40)
  - Willard, Elizabeth (Box 40)
  - Willard, Margaretta M (Box 40)
    (Mrs. DeForest P.)
  - Willard, Theodore A (Box 40)
  - Willets, Jane (Box 40)
  - Willey, Gordon R (Box 40)
  - Williams, Albert (Box 40)
  - Williams, Alfred H (Box 40)
  - Williams, Charles (Box 40)
  - Williams, Edwin B (Box 40)
  - Williams, Elgin (Box 40)
  - Williams, Frances M (Box 40)
  - Williams, J. J (Box 40)
  - Williams, Milford (Box 40)
  - Williams, Mrs. John C., Jr (Box 40)
  - Willis, William S (Box 40)
  - Willitz, C. O (Box 40)
  - Willoughby, C. C (Box 40)
  - Wills, H. L (Box 40)
  - Wilson, A. M (Box 40)
  - Wilson, Jonathan D (Box 40)
  - Wilson, Mrs. F. E (Box 40)
  - Winfield, Armand G (Box 40)
  - Wingert, Paul S (Box 40)
  - Winkler Pepe, Braz Francisco (Box 40)
    - DeBiase, Attilio (Box 40)
  - Winlock, Herbert E (Box 40)
  - Winn, Vetal (Box 40)
  - Winter, William J (Box 40)
  - Winterbotham, George S. & Associates (Box 40)
    - Newell, David (Box 40)
  - Winters, H. A (Box 40)
    - Mosley, E. L (Box 40)
    - Winters, Edith (Box 40)
  - Winters, Howard D (Box 40)
  - Wintersteen, Mrs. A H (Box 40)
  - Wisdom, Charles (Box 40)
  - Wise, John C (Box 40)
  - Wissler, Clark (Box 40)
    - Cooper, John M (Box 40)
    - Guthe, Carl (Box 40)
  - Wistar Institute (Box 40)
    - Greenman, W J (Box 40)
    - McHugh, Jane (Box 40)
    - Perrine, C N (Box 40)
  - Withers, Carl (Box 40)
  - Withey, Raymond A, Jr (Box 40)
  - Witmer, B. Frank (Box 40)
  - Witmer, Edward B (Box 40)
  - Witte Memorial Museum (Box 40)
    - Gutzeit, Emma (Box 40)
  - Witte, Harry L., Jr (Box 40)
  - Witte, William Cole (Box 40)
  - Witte, William H (Box 40)
  - Witthoft, John, 1945-1956; 2 folders (Box 40)
  - Wittry, Warren L (Box 40)
  - Wixon, Darvey (Box 40)
  - Wolf, Berdina (Box 40)
  - Wolf, Minnie Marks (Box 40)
  - Wolfe, Alvin W (Box 40)
  - Wolff, Werner (Box 40)
    - Wardle, Harriet Newell (Box 40)
  - Wolford, Tom (Box 40)
  - Wonderly, William L (Box 40)
  - Wood, W. B (Box 40)
  - Woodman, Elizabeth A (Box 40)
  - Woodman, Walter J (Box 40)
  - Woods, Lawrence C, Jr (Box 40)
  - Woodward, Arthur (Box 40)
  - Woodward, Mrs. Frank D (Box 40)
  - Woodward, Wright and Co (Box 40)
  - Woolverton, Laura (Box 40)
  - Wormington conference on museums and anthropology, 1954 (Box 40)
  - Wormington, H. M (Box 40)
  - Wormington, H. Marie (Box 40)
  - Worrall, Ashton Locke (Box 40)
  - Worth, Alice (Box 40)
  - Worth, Mary (Box 40)
  - Wright, Berlin Hart (Box 40)
  - Wright, Brainard (Box 40)
  - Wright, Cecil D (Box 40)
  - Wright, Frances (Box 40)
  - Wright, Harry Bernard (Box 40)
    - Buck, Peter Henry (Box 40)
    - Huettenmoser, C (Box 40)
    - Molded Insulation Co (Box 40)
  - Wright, Richard (Box 40)
  - Wright, Ross Pier (Box 40)
    - Dorrance, Frances (Box 40)
  - Wrigley, Gladys M (Box 40)
  - Wroth,Laurence C (Box 40)
  - Yale University Art Gallery (Box 40)
  - Yde, Jens (Box 40)
  - Yenghin, Oswald (Box 40)
  - Yenny, W W (Box 40)
  - Yorke, James (Box 40)
  - Yost, Mary (Box 40)
  - Young, Donald R (Box 40)
    - Shryock, Richard H (Box 40)
  - The Young Men's Christian Assoc., Ashland, Ohio (Box 40)
    - Martin, Stuart A
  - Yust, Waldo (Box 40)
  - Zaballos Menendez, Carlos (Box 40)
  - Zanko, Mrs. Jewel (Box 40)
  - Zanotti, Vittorio (Box 40)
  - Zavala, Lauro Jose (Box 40)
  - Zelosophic Society (Box 40)
    - Sharfman, Herbert (Box 40)
  - Zeper, Roy (Box 40)
  - Zevallos, Carmen Ortiz de (Box 40)
  - Zim, Sonia Bleeker (Box 40)
  - Zimmerman, M W (Box 40)
  - Zingg, Robert M (Box 40)
    - Zingg, Mrs. O. C (Box 40)
    - Jayne, Horace (Box 40)
  - Ziskovsky, A J (Box 40)
- Series II. Latin American Institute for Race and Culture Studies, 1921, 1934-1936; 0.5 linear feet
  Minutes and correspondence of the Advisory Committee and general correspondence, along with reports on the mission and progress of the short-lived Latin-American Institute for Race and Culture Studies, an organization to promote study of the rapidly acculturating Indians of South and Central America.
  - Correspondence, Advisory Council, 1934 (Box 1)
  - Advisory Council Members, 1934 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, Advisory Council, 1935 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, General, 1935 (Box 1)
  - History, Policies, Projects, Organization, 1935 (Box 1)
  - Membership, General, 1934-1936 (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous, ca.1935 (Box 1)
  - Original proposal, Outline of policies, 1934-1935 (Box 1)
  - Projects and ideas, 1921, 1935 (Box 1)
  - Publication of "Memorandum", 1935 (Box 1)
  - What and Why?, ca.1935 (Box 1)
- Series III. Linguistics, 1935-1958; 1 linear foot
  A mixed assemblage of materials, including a small amount of correspondence, relating primarily to Mason's linguistic interests, and particularly to Pima Bajo, Northern Tepehuan, Papago, and his work on South American linguistics in the early 1950s. The series was combined from two accessions received from Mason's estate. Correspondence and photographs associated with the series have been transferred to Series I and VII, respectively.
  Immediate Source of Acquisition note
  Originally received as two accessions from the estate of John Alden Mason, 1968, now combined.
  - Appraisal of American objects in Brooklyn Museum on loan from New York Historical Society. Personal (Box 1)
  - Comparative lists from Southern and Northern dialects of Tepehuan, Bascom, Burton W., Jr. (Box 1)
  - Brugge-Annon trip to Sonora: Log, ininerary, list of photos, journal, Brugge, David M. (Box 1)
  - History of the Pima Bajo of the mountains, Brugge, David M. (Box 1)
  - Lower Pima (Pima Bajo);Notes, Brugge, David M. (Box 1)
  - Nevome (=Pima Bajo) Word Lists, Brugge, David M. (Box 1)
  - Cave investigations in Durango and Coahuila (Box 1)
  - Central American Linguistics, miscellaneous (Box 1)
  - Cucurbita moschata in Sonora, Mexico (Box 1)
  - Northern Tepehuan myth, Dolores, Juan (Box 1)
  - Notebook No. 14, Dolores, Juan (Box 1)
  - Papago Texts, 7 folders; Dolores, Juan (Box 1)
  - Durango Archeology (Kelley, Schroeder Site) (Box 1)
  - Durango Expedition., 1935 (Box 1)
  - Durango. (Some Archeology and Ethnology in this area.) (Box 1)
  - Ecuadorean Oriente (Box 1)
  - Escuela Internacional de Etnologia y Arqueologia Americanas, Preliminary Report as Fellow to the., 1912-13 (Box 1)
  - Fifty years of American anthropology (Wenner-Gren talk, 1957) (Box 1)
  - Garcia, Miguel. (Corrected by Dolores). Papago text (Box 1)
  - Gerald. APS Research, 1955 (Box 1)
  - Geographical distribution of the Native languages and dialects of Peru, Garro, J. Eugenio (Box 1)
  - Handbook of South American Indians, Correspondence (Box 1)
  - Adjectivelderivational suffixes of Quechua, Harrington, John Peabody (Box 1)
  - Affiliation of the Cholon language, Harrington, John Peabody (Box 1)
  - Affiliation of Witoto, Miranyan, and Guaranian, Harrington, John Peabody (Box 1)
  - Cocama Epitome., [1943]; Harrington, John Peabody (Box 1)
  - Correspondence between... and J. Alden Mason., May 19, 1943-June 21, 1944; Harrington, John Peabody (Box 1)
  - Grammarlets of the Quechua and Cocama languages., [1943]; Harrington, John Peabody (Box 1)
  - Jibaro Epitome., [1943]; Harrington, John Peabody (Box 1)
  - The nominal derivational suffixes of Quechua, Harrington, John Peabody (Box 1)
  - South American linguistics: Miranya, Witoto, Tupi-Guarani affiliations, Harrington, John Peabody (Box 1)
  - Uru-Puquina., [1943]; Harrington, John Peabody (Box 1)
  - A.P.S. Indian linguistic material: Central America, Mexico, South America, Harris, Zellig S., (Zellig Sabbettai), 1909- (Box 2)
  - Heye, George G (Box 2)
  - Hobgood-Riley. Visit to Santa Maria Ocotlan (Box 2)
  - Huichol-Cora comparisons (Box 2)
  - Linguistic groupings in Middle America, Johnson, Frederick (Box 2)
  - Uto-Aztecan-Polynesian linguistic comparisons, Kelly, David H. (Box 2)
  - Kinship terms: Southern Tepehuan, Northern Tepehuan, and Tepecano (Box 2)
  - Kurath, William. A brief introduction to Papago (Box 2)
  - Language discoveries (from publications) (Box 2)
  - Languages "South American Handbook (Box 2)
  - Lauriault, Erwin H. Shipibo myths and analysis; correspondence with J. Alden Mason (Box 2)
  - Lehmann, Walter. Zental-Amerika. Digest and translation by Weinberger (Box 2)
  - Leon, Nicolas. Familias linguisticas de Mexico: idiomas y dialectos a ellas pertencientes (Box 2)
    Related Archival Materials note
    See also map filed in extra-oversize drawers under ACLS (497.3.B63c): "Sinopsis de las familias idiomas y dialectos de las lenguas indigenas de México según la clasificación del Dr. Nicolás León." "Bosquejo de la carta lingüística de México según la clasificación del Dr. Nicolás León." A printed map, in color. No imprint, no date. [Map not cataloged as of January 2013.]
  - Liaisons between linguistics and archeology (Box 2)
  - Los Cuatro Grandes Filones Linguisticos de Mexico y Centroamerica (Box 2)
  - Lower Pima. Notes, etc. for recent article (Box 2)
  - Mexican linguistics: comparative vocabularies, etc (Box 2)
  - Middle American languages: Notes on genetic relationships and geographic distribution taken from published sources (Box 2)
  - Middle American languages (Box 2)
  - Middle American linguistics, 1955 (Box 2)
  - Museum technique class -- linguistics (Box 2)
  - Nevome (Lower Pima Expedition), 1953 (Box 3)
  - Nevome grammatical notes (Box 3)
  - Northern Tepehuan Linguistic Expedition, Finances, 1951. (Box 3)
  - Northern Tepehuan Linguistic Expedition, Report, 1951. (Box 3)
  - Northern Tepehuan Texts (Box 3)
  - Notes on numerical systems. (Uto-Aztecan) (Box 3)
  - Notes on the Linguistic and Cultural Affiliations of the Tepehuan and Tepecano (Box 3)
  - Notes on the Northern Extension of the Calchihuites Culture (Box 3)
  - Papago field notes (Box 3)
  - Papago grammatical notes (Box 3)
  - Papago grammatical notes, 3 folders (Box 3)
  - Papago miscellaneous notes, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Papago myths in translation (English) (Box 3)
  - Papago nominal stems ending in l, li, or t. (Box 3)
  - Papago songs and ethnographic notes (Box 3)
  - Papago stops (Box 3)
  - Papago texts (Box 3)
  - Papago: General characteristics (Box 3)
  - Perdones Tepehuanes (Box 3)
  - Pima-Papago and Tepehuan, correspondence in regard to (Box 3)
  - Pittman's Practical Linguistics (Box 3)
  - Preliminary sketch of the Yaqui language (Box 3)
  - Problems of Mexican linguistics for study (Box 3)
  - A Sketch of Tepecano Religion (Box 4)
  - Some Archeological sites near Rancho Guiracoba, Sonora, Mexico (Box 4)
  - Some initial phones and combinations in Utaztecan stems (Box 4)
  - Some initial phones and combinations in Utaztecan stems: correspondence (Box 4)
  - South American Languages(data) (Box 4)
  - South American linguistics, Schmidt (Box 4)
  - South American linguistics. Centers of Genitivnachstellung in South America (Box 4)
  - South American linguistics. Comparison of Rivet's classification with that of Loukotka (Box 4)
  - South American linguistics. Coroado-Ge resemblances (Box 4)
  - South American linguistics. Coropo vocabulary (Box 4)
  - South American linguistics. Ge (Box 4)
  - South American linguistics. Kaduveo-Mataco correspondences (Box 4)
  - South American linguistics. Kamakan (Box 4)
  - South American linguistics. List of Macro-Ges vocabularies (Box 4)
  - South American linguistics. Malali vocabulary (Box 4)
  - South American linguistics. Malali-Mashakali-Ge-Kaingang comparisons (Box 4)
  - South American linguistics. Matacoan and Towothli (Box 4)
  - South American linguistics. Mataco-Mataguayo, etc (Box 4)
  - South American linguistics. Motilon-Spanish vocabulary (Box 4)
  - South American linguistics. Patasho vocabulary (Box 4)
  - South American linguistics. Set-up, bibliography, etc (Box 4)
  - South American linguistics. Tessman. N. E. Peru (Box 4)
  - South American linguistics. Working data and digests (Box 4)
  - Southern Illinois Library. Kelley, Lange (Durango Trip) (Box 4)
  - Status and problems of research in the Native Languages of South America (Box 4)
  - Swanton word list (Box 4)
  - Swanton, John R. Digest from letter (Box 4)
  - Tarahumare-Cahita comparisons (Box 4)
  - Tepecano Rain Festival Song (Box 4)
  - Tepecano verbal roots (Box 4)
  - Tepehuan Archeology and Ethnology (Box 4)
  - Tepehuan Wire and Tape Records (Box 4)
  - Tepehuan Wire Records (notes) (Box 4)
  - Tepehuan, Northern, miscellaneous notes (Box 4)
  - Tepehuan, Northern, Morphology (Box 4)
  - Tepehuan, Northern, myths and other texts (Box 4)
  - Tepehuan-Tepecano-Huichol-Cora comparative vocabulary (Box 4)
  - The Primitive Religions of Mexico (Box 4)
  - Utaztecan sound shifts, [1951] (Box 4)
  - Uto-Aztecan comparative vocabularies: Nahua, Yaqui, Opata, Huichol, Tepecano, Papago (Box 4)
  - Uto-Aztecan comparative vocabularies: Tarahumare, Yaqui, Tepecano, Aztec (Box 4)
  - Uto-Aztecan comparative vocabularies: Tubar, Heve, Tarahumara, Yaqui (Box 4)
  - Uto-Aztecan: Lexicostatistical compilations and comparative vocabulary (Box 4)
  - Uto-Aztecan: Miscellany (Box 4)
  - Comparative vocabulary, Weitlaner, Robert (Box 4)
  - Weitlaner, Robert J. Hokano:Otomangue:Yuto-Azteca:Mayance (Box 4)
  - Linguistic realignment north of Mexico, Whorf, Benjamin L. (Box 4)
  - Macro-Penutian, Whorf, Benjamin L. (Box 4)
  - Utaztecan, Whorf, Benjamin L. (Box 4)
  - Wire Records, Microfilm notes (Tepehuan) (copy of notes under Tepehuan wire records) (Box 4)
  - Yaqui notes (published sources) (Box 4)
  - Yaqui texts #1 (Box 4)
  - Yaqui texts #2 (Box 4)
- Series IV. Card Files and Notebooks, 1911-1951; 3 linear feet
  Bibliographies and card files relating primarily to Mason's linguistic research. Among the notebooks are a valuable set of eight volumes of linguistic notes taken during Mason's research among the Tepecano in Jalisco, Mexico, 1911-1912, and two volumes relating to his postdoctoral research on Salinan linguistics in 1916-1917.
  - Not used, 1
  - Papago linguistics card file, 2; 2 boxes
  - Northern Tepehuan linguistics file, 3; 3x5. ca.350 cards.
  - Pima Bajo linguistics notes (alphabetically arranged), 4
  - Tepecano linguistic file, 5; ca.500 cards. 3x5.
  - Bibliography of South American Indians, 6; ca.300 cards. 4x5
  - South American linguistic and ethnology notes, 7; ca.2,000 cards. 3x5.
  - South American linguistic notes. ca.4,000 cards. 3x5 and other sizes, 8
  - Miscellaneous notes on Tepecan. Ethnology, linguistics, and principally religion. Piman characteristics, etc., 9; ca.150 items
    "Work done for Boas."
  - Notebooks, 1911-1951; 10; 0.5 linear feet
    - Digest of... Tepehuan in Ayres... Newberry, 1 vol., 1 vol. 8.75x5.25", red lea. binding
    - Expense accounts, 1935-1936
    - Northern Tepehuan Linguistic notebooks, 1951; 2 vols., 9x6"
      Babongame, Chihuahua, Mexico. One vol. entitled "Texts from Wire Records," the other "Misc. No wire records."
    - Northern Tepehuan Linguistics, 1936; 2 vols. 9x6.75"
      Taken at Guanaceni, Durango.
    - Salinan Ethnology and Linguistics, December 1916; 1 vol.
      Work done for Kroeber and completed 12/'16
    - Salinan Ethnology and linguistics, December 1917; 1 vol.
      Work done for Kroeber and completed 12/'17
    - South American Indian notes (compiled unknown), 1 vol., 10.5x7.5"
    - Southern Tepehuan field notesD, 1948; 7 vols. 9x6.5"
      Some contain transcriptions and translations of wire recordings.